When, in 1960, still a student,
في 1960، حين كنت لا أزال طالبًا
I got a traveling fellowship
حصلت على منحة سفر
to study housing in North America.
لدراسة الإسكان في شمال أمريكا.
We traveled the country.
سافرنا عبر البلاد.
We saw public housing high-rise buildings
رأينا العمارات الشاهقة للإسكان العام
in all major cities:
في كل المدن الكبرى:
New York, Philadelphia.
نيويورك، فيلاديلفيا.
Those who have no choice lived there.
الذين من دون أي خيار عاشوا هناك.
And then we traveled from suburb to suburb,
ثم سافرنا من ضاحية لضاحية
and I came back thinking,
وعدنا مفكرين انه
we've got to reinvent the apartment building.
يجب ان نخترع من جديد البنايات السكنية.
There has to be another way of doing this.
يجب ان يكون هناك طريقة اخرى للقيام بهذا.
We can't sustain suburbs,
لا يمكننا الحفاظ على الضواحي
so let's design a building
لذلك دعونا نصمم مبنى
which gives the qualities of a house
الذي يعطي صفات منزل
to each unit.
لكل وحدة
Habitat would be all about gardens,
سيكون السكن "هابيتات" كله عن الحدائق،
streets instead of corridors.
الشوارع بدلا من الممرات،
We prefabricated it so we would achieve economy,
جهزناه مقدما لكي نحقق الاقتصاد
and there it is almost 50 years later.
وها هو، بعد حوالي 50 عاما.
It's a very desirable place to live in.
انه مكان مرغوب فيه للغاية للعيش فيه.
It's now a heritage building,
انه الآن مبنى تراثي،
but it did not proliferate.
لكنه لم ينتشر.
In 1973, I made my first trip to China.
في عام 1973، قمت برحلتي الأولى إلى الصين
It was the Cultural Revolution.
وكانت الثورة الثقافية.
We traveled the country,
سافرنا عبر البلد
met with architects and planners.
التقينا بالمهندسين المعماريين والمخططين.
This is Beijing then,
هذه بكين في تلك الفترة
not a single high rise building
ولا حتى مبنى شاهق واحد
in Beijing or Shanghai.
في بكين او شانغهاي.
Shenzhen didn't even exist as a city.
شنتشن لم تكن موجودة حتى كمدينة.
There were hardly any cars.
يكاد لا يكون هناك أي سيارات.
Thirty years later,
بعد ثلاثين عاما،
this is Beijing today.
هذه هي بكين اليوم.
This is Hong Kong.
هذه هي هونغ كونغ.
If you're wealthy, you live there,
إذا كنت ثريا، تعيش هناك،
if you're poor, you live there,
إذا كنت فقيرا، تعيش هناك،
but high density it is, and it's not just Asia.
لكنها عالية الكثافة، وانها ليست مجرد آسيا.
São Paulo, you can travel
ساو باولو، يمكنك السفر
in a helicopter 45 minutes
في طائرة هليكوبتر 45 دقيقة
seeing those high-rise buildings consume
رؤية تلك المباني الشاهقة تستهلك
the 19th-century low-rise environment.
بيئة القرن 19 المنخفضة الارتفاع.
And with it, comes congestion,
ومعها ياتي الازدحام
and we lose mobility, and so on and so forth.
ونفقد الحركية، وهكذا دواليك.
So a few years ago, we decided to go back
قبل بضع سنين، قررنا الرجوع
and rethink Habitat.
واعادة التفكير في المبني "هابيتات".
Could we make it more affordable?
هل بامكاننا جعله في المتناول؟
Could we actually achieve this quality of life
هل بامكاننا تحقيق هذه الجودة في الحياة
And we realized, it's basically about light,
وادركنا انه في الاساس حول الضوء
it's about fractalization.
انه حول الفراكتالات
Can we open up the surface of the building
هل يمكننا ان نفتح مساحة المبنى
so that it has more contact with the exterior?
لكي يكون له اتصال اكثر مع الخارج
We came up with a number of models:
اتينا بالعديد من النماذج:
economy models, cheaper to build and more compact;
نماذج اقتصادية، ارخص في البناء واكثر التماما
membranes of housing
اغشية البناء
where people could design their own house
يمكن عندها للناس تصميم منازلهم
and create their own gardens.
وخلق حدائقهم
And we mapped all the building area in Manhattan.
وقمنا بتعيين جميع مباني المنطقة في مانهاتن
On the left is Manhattan today:
على اليسار، مانهاتن اليوم
blue for housing, red for office buildings, retail.
زرقاء للمباني، حمراء للمكاتب، التجزيئ.
On the right, we reconfigured it:
على اليمين، قمنا باعادة تكوينها
the office buildings form the base,
مباني المكاتب من الاساس
and then rising 75 stories above,
ومن ثم على ارتفاع 75 طابقا بالأعلى
There's a street in the air on the 25th level,
هناك شارع في الهواء على مستوى 25
a community street.
شارع اجتماعي.
It's permeable.
انه قابل للولوج.
for the community,
للمجتمع.
almost every unit with its own private garden,
تقريبا كل وحدة بحديقتها الخاصة
and community space all around.
وفضاء مجتمعي حولها.
And most important, permeable, open.
والاكثر اهمية، قابلة للولوج، مفتوحة.
It does not form a wall or an obstruction in the city,
لا تشكل جدارا او مانعا في المدينة،
and light permeates everywhere.
الضوء يتخلل كل مكان.
And in the last two or three years,
في السنتين او ثلاثة السابقة
we've actually been, for the first time,
لقد، للمرة الاولى
realizing the quality of life of Habitat
نحقق جودة الحياة التي في "هابيتات"
in real-life projects across Asia.
في مشاريع واقعية عبر آسيا.
This in Qinhuangdao in China:
هذه في تشينهوانغداو في الصين:
middle-income housing, where there is a bylaw
سكن ذوي الدخل المتوسط، حيث يوجد قانون داخلي
three hours of sunlight.
ثلاثة ساعات من ضوء الشمس.
That's measured in the winter solstice.
يتم قياس هذا في الانقلاب الشتوي
And under construction in Singapore,
وفي طور البناء في سنغافورة،
again middle-income housing, gardens,
من جديد، سكن ذوي الدخل المتوسط، حدائق
community streets and parks and so on and so forth.
شوارع عامة، متنزهات، الخ.
And Colombo.
و كلومبو.
And I want to touch on one more issue,
وأريد لمس مشكلة واحدة أخرى.
which is the design of the public realm.
وهو تصميم الاماكن العمومية.
A hundred years after we've begun building
بعد مائة عام من البدء في بناء
with tall buildings,
المباني العالية،
we are yet to understand
مازلنا نحتاج فهم
how the tall high-rise building
كيف يصبح البناء العالي
becomes a building block in making a city,
حجر اساس في بناء مدينة،
in creating the public realm.
في خلق المجال العمومي
In Singapore, we had an opportunity:
في سنغافورة، اتيحت لنا فرصة:
10 million square feet, extremely high density.
10 ملايين قدم مربع، وكثافة عالية جدا.
Taking the concept of outdoor and indoor,
باعتبار مبدا الداخل والخارج
promenades and parks integrated
تم ادراج اماكن التجوال و الحدائق
with intense urban life.
مع العمران الكثيف.
So they are outdoor spaces and indoor spaces,
اذن هنالك اماكن مفتوحة ومغلقة
and you move from one to the other,
وتتنقل من الواحدة الى الاخرى،
and there is contact with nature,
وهناك اتصال بالطبيعة،
and most relevantly, at every level of the structure,
والاكثر أهمية، أنه على جميع أصعدة البنية،
public gardens and open space:
الحدائق العمومية والاماكن المفتوحة.
on the roof of the podium,
على سطح المنصة،
climbing up the towers,
صعودا على الابراج،
and finally on the roof, the sky park,
وفي النهاية على السقف، الحديقة
two and a half acres, jogging paths, restaurants,
فدانين ونصف، مسارات الركض، والمطاعم،
and the world's longest swimming pool.
واطول مسبح في العالم.
And that's all I can tell you in five minutes.
وهذا كل ما استطيع قوله في خمس دقائق.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)